Guide to the David Knapp Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Knapp papers
1944-2014
1984-2014
MS 1940
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
12 boxes
1976.23
The papers consist of an oral history interview, newspaper clippings, correspondence, legal documents, and video recordings documenting the activism of David Knapp for gay and lesbian rights. The bulk of the papers concern Knapp's involvement in efforts to change the Boy Scouts of America's (BSA) position on homosexuality. Knapp's oral history provides an overview of his life, providing a rich source of information on his youth, family life, career, discovery of his homosexuality, and activism. The papers also contain newspaper clippings on various gay and lesbian issues but very little on the gay and lesbian organizations in which Knapp is involved.
Knapp, David, 1926-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Knapp, 2009-2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Copies of commercially produced audiovisual materials contained in this collection cannot be made for researcher use outside of the repository.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Biographical / Historical
David Knapp was born in New York City on September 2, 1926. He joined the Boy Scouts of America (BSA) at the age of twelve and later worked for the BSA in volunteer and professional positions for many years. He graduated from Wesleyan University in 1949. He has been an active church member throughout his adult life. Knapp married Mary Adelaide Wheeler in 1958, becoming a stepfather to her two daughters. A year later, they had another daughter. After he married, he left his professional position at the BSA and became a salesman. Knapp moved his family to Connecticut in 1970 to pursue career advancement.
Knapp discovered he was gay in the late 1970s at the age of fifty. Ten years later, he and his wife divorced. Knapp was outed to the BSA and to his church by family members and was consequently expelled by both organizations. His experiences prompted him to become an activist for gay and lesbian rights. He is engaged in a long term campaign to change the BSA position on homosexuality. He is involved in Scouting For All, an organization that also seeks to make the BSA welcoming of gay boys and men. He led his church, the First Church of Christ of Guilford, in its efforts to become open and affirming. He is a member and former leader of Stonewall Speakers, a Connecticut-based lesbian/gay/bisexual/transgender speakers bureau. Additionally, Knapp started GLSEN (Gay, Lesbian and Straight Education Network) and PFLAG (Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays) chapters in Connecticut. [Source: David Knapp Oral History, 2007]
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of an oral history interview, newspaper clippings, correspondence, legal documents, and video recordings documenting the activism of David Knapp for gay and lesbian rights. The bulk of the papers concern Knapp's involvement in efforts to change the Boy Scouts of America's (BSA) position on homosexuality. Knapp's oral history provides an overview of his life, providing a rich source of information on his youth, family life, career, discovery of his homosexuality, and activism. The papers also contain newspaper clippings on various gay and lesbian issues but very little on the gay and lesbian organizations in which Knapp is involved.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by topic.
Coming out (Sexual orientation) -- United States; Gay men -- Family relationships; Gay men -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Gay men -- Connecticut; Gays -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Homophobia; Outing (Sexual orientation) -- United States; LGBTQ resource; Knapp, David, 1926-; Boy Scouts of America -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Boy Scouts of America
- David Knapp, oral history conducted by Cynthia Braver
  - PFLAG (Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays), 1993-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Part 1, 2007 November 10; Computer file (QuickTime) (Box 13)
    Scope and Contents
    Part 1 covers Knapp's boyhood in New Jersey, his parents and his relationship with them, his love of the outdoors and becoming a boy scout.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
    - Use copy, Compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 1U)
  - Part 2, 2007 November 10; Computer file (QuickTime) (Box 14)
    Part 2 covers Knapp's young adult years, living through the depression, attending high school during World War II, being a boy scout camp counselor, and student life at Wesleyan University.
    - Use copy, Compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 2U)
  - Part 3, 2007 November 10; Computer file (QuickTime) (Box 15)
    Part 3 covers Knapp's trip to Europe after graduation, graduate work at Rutgers University and attaining his teaching certificate, student teaching, working for the BSA as District Executive, marriage, family life, work as a salesman, move to Connecticut, discoving he was gay, coming out, divorce, and being outed.
    - Use copy, Compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 3U)
  - Part 4, 2007 November 10; Computer file (QuickTime) (Box 16)
    Part 4 covers Knapp's life after divorce, his move to Guilford, Connecticut, senior years, joining gay or gay friendly organizations, his relationship with his boyfriend, hiking, sailing, the Stonewall Speakers, the First Congregational Church of Guilford, GLSEN, being expelled from the BSA, publicity surrounding his expulsion, his activism, and Scouting for All.
    - Use copy, Compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 4U)
- Boy Scouts of America (BSA)
  - Writings by Knapp, 1994, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Articles featuring Knapp, 1994-2014 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1944-2005, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Commission of Human Rights and Opportunities, 1987-2003 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scouting for All
    - Printed material, circa 2002-2006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "The Boy Scouts," Penn & Teller: Bullshit!, commercially produced optical disk (DVD), undated (Box 7)
    - Scouting for All Protest Connecticut--News August 21, 2000, commercially produced videotape (VHS), circa 2000 (Box 8)
    - Steven Cozza speech; PFLAG Presents: Scouting for All; Scout's Honor, circa 2000; 1 (Box 9)
  - General, 1948-2006
    - Pamphlets, miscellaneous printed material, circa 1980s-2002 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Articles, 1986-2006, undated (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
    - "The Boy Scouts" ( 60 Minutes ), commercially produced videotape (VHS), 2001 April 01 (Box 10)
    - Scout's Honor Tom Shepard, Director, Plus 60 Minutes BSA, commercially produced videotape (VHS), 2001 (Box 11)
- Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender issues
  - Correspondence, 1996, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clipping and printed material, 1984-2003, undated (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
- Stonewall Speakers
  - General, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Stonewall Speakers, 2006 December 8; videotape (VHS) (Box 12)
- United Church of Christ, 1985-2002 (Box 6, Folder 6)